<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some testimonies of the life, death and sufferings of Amariah Drewet of Cirencester in Gloucestershire, lately deceased and to the way of life wherein he walked, whose living words upon his dying bed are worthy to be had in remembrance.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52031</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40454</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19334873</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19334873</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108668</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52031)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108668)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1674:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some testimonies of the life, death and sufferings of Amariah Drewet of Cirencester in Gloucestershire, lately deceased and to the way of life wherein he walked, whose living words upon his dying bed are worthy to be had in remembrance.</title>
                  <author>Drewet, Mary.</author>
                  <author>Drewet, John.</author>
                  <author>Marshall, Charles, 1637-1698.</author>
                  <author>Townsend, Theophila.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andrew Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687 [i.e. 1688]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Four short tributes signed: Mary Drewet (p. 6), John Drewet (p. 7), Theophila Townsend (p. 14), Charles Marshall (p. 16).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped and stained, with print show-through and slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Drewet, Amariah.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England.</term>
               <term>Last words.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108668:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME TESTIMONIES OF THE Life, Death and Sufferings OF <hi>Amariah Drewet,</hi> OF CIRENCESTER, IN <hi>Glouceſterſhire,</hi> lately Deceaſed; AND To the way of Life wherein he walked.</p>
            <p>Whoſe Living Words upon his Dying Bed are worthy to be had in Remembrance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, by <hi>Andrew Sowle,</hi> in the Year 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="testimonies">
            <pb facs="tcp:108668:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:108668:2"/>
            <head>A Teſtimony of the Life, Death and Sufferings of <hi>Amariah Drewet,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>Mary Drewet<hi>'s Teſtimony concerning her Husband.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Being ſo nearly Related as a Wife to <hi>Amariah Drewet,</hi> have this Teſtimony to bear for him: He was a Lover of the Truth, and all the Upright-hearted that Lived in it, they were near and dear unto him; there is a few Words that lives in the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleneſs of my Heart, as a ſhort Teſtimony of his Innocent Life, and the Good Savour that was with him on his Death-Bed: The Lord brought us together in his Fear, and in the Love of the precious Truth wherein we were Joyned we Lived in true Unity, the Days the Lord gave us together; and although the Lord was pleaſed to remove him to my great loſs, which in the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a deep Exerciſe; but there is cauſe of Joy and Comfort as my Eye is to the Lord, being ſatisfied in his well-being: He was a tender Husband and Father to my Children which I had by a former Husband: (who alſo in his day was a Man Fearing God, and a Lover of Truth) I can truly ſay, to the Praiſe of the Name of the Lord, that his Life and Converſation Preached, and his Moderation was known to moſt where he Lived, that the Lord was at hand; and according to the meaſure the Lord had given him ſince he knew the Truth, he was Faithful in his Day, and turned not his Back in the time of Suffering; but willingly, and with cheerfulneſs was given up, and rather Bleſſed the Name of the Lord that he was found worthy to be one of that Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to have his Faith tryed before the Lord, and alſo before his Perſecutors, often deſiring the Lord to forgive them, and that they might come to ſee the Evil of their Ways, and turn to the Lord by true Repentance, that they might find Favour with him: He was a plain hearted Man, and hated all Deceit and Pride where
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108668:3"/>ever it appeared, and thoſe that kept in the true plainneſs were very near unto him, the remembrance of it hath deep impreſſion on my Heart, in the conſideration of the goodneſs of the Lord, what he is to thoſe that fear him, and are of an Upright Heart; their latter end is not like the Wicked, as this my dear Husband was made a Living Witneſs of; and it pleaſed the Lord to give him a double Portion of his Spirit, the Hundred fold in this Life, as a full Reward in his own Boſom, according to his Promiſe, and in that which is to come Life Everlaſting.</p>
               <p>On the 11th Day of the 7th Month 1687. it pleaſed the Lord to viſit him with Sickneſs, and a Feavor came on, but very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate; that in all his Sickneſs, when asked how he was, he would anſwer, <hi>Pretty Well, and not much in Pain;</hi> which was a great pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge as to the outward Man; but that Life which excelleth all, which indeed was Health in Sickneſs, and is over Death, Hell and the Grave, and is Everlaſting, the Lord in a large mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure made him partaker of, and ſo filled his Soul with his Love that he did often Sing for Joy of Heart; and as Friends came in to viſit him, his Heart would be often opened with freſh Springs of Life, and break forth with ſweet Praiſes, Magnifying the worthy Name of the Lord, and his Power that he had made him a Witneſs of, to the Refreſhment of the Upright-hearted; and alſo a Word of Exhortation was given him, as there was occaſion, when People came in to viſit him, to the tendering of their Hearts; he gave ſweet Counſel to my Children, Exhorting them <hi>to live in the Fear of God, and love the Truths</hi> And about three days before he De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, he broke forth with Praiſes to the Lord, again ſignifying, if it were the laſt Teſtimony he had to bare, that the <hi>Love and Preſence, and Peace of God was with him;</hi> and that he could as truly ſay, as good old <hi>Simeon, That he had ſeen the Salvation of God:</hi> The Night before he Departed, being in a ſweet frame of Spirit ſaid, <hi>My dear Wiſe, be not caſt down nor troubled, the Lord intends Good to thee;</hi> deſiring me to go to Bed, and ſaid, <hi>I had need of Reſt,</hi> and gave me up to the Lord whoſe Preſence I feel, <hi>and I reſign up thee, and the Keeper of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>the good Watchman that never Slumbers nor Sleeps be with thee.</hi> This in great tenderneſs he ſpoke; ſo we took our Leave of each other, and the greateſt part of that Night, after he had been a little in a Slumber, he would awake with ſweet
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108668:3"/>Praiſes in his Mouth, for the largeneſs of the loving Kindneſs of the Lord that he felt, and early in the Morning when I came to him, he told me, he had been ſweetly Refreſhed this Night, and bleſſed the Name of the Lord that let him Live to ſee this Day, and that he had given his People a little time of Liberty and Reſt to wait upon the Lord, deſiring they might prize it, and be Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful he often deſired his dear Love to be remembred to all Friends, eſpecially to thoſe travilling Friends that he had moſt acquaintance with, and that had frequented his Houſe; he continued Senſible to the laſt, and ſtill with renewed Praiſes to the Lord; and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Evening, being the 25th of the 7th Month 1687. and about the Sixtieth Year of his Age, he departed this Life. Theſe things are not Written to take any thing to Self, but forever I deſire to lie low before the Lord, and to his Name and Power, that was manifeſt through his Servant that's taken from me, be the Honour and Praiſe for evermore; and alſo that it might be an Invitation to ſuch as have any tender deſires after the Lord, and are yet Strangers to his Way, that they may know and ſee how good the Lord is to them that Fear him, and have believed in and obeyed the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, that he hath placed in every Man and Womans Conſcience, as a Reprover of every Evil Word and Work, that they may come to believe in it and obey its Requirings, that they may be made pertakers of the ſame Salvation to their own Comfort and Well-being forever. So de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring the Lord may be with me, and bare up my Head, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry me through my new Exerciſes which the Lord ſees good to try me withal, in a true Submiſſion to his Will, which Bleſſed be the Lord, as my Eye is turned towards him, and my Mind ſtaid upon him, his ſecret Hand doth uphold me. O that I, with all the Lords People that are left a little behind, may be diligent to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Lord in all things that he requires of us, and that we may be good Examples in our places, and before our Children in all manner of plainneſs, as becomes the Truth, for this Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion paſſeth faſt away; ſo that they may come up in our room to ſerve the Lord, and bare a Teſtimony for his Truth, that they may be made pertakers of this bleſſed Inheritance that ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fade away, and that the Lord has prepared for them that Love and Serve him, which this my dear Husband did in his day,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108668:4"/>according to the meaſure God had given him, and is row entered into his Reſt, where his Praiſe is ſure forever with the Lord, and his Memorial will Live in the Hearts of the Upright, although his Body is taken from us, and returned to its own Center.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Mary Drewet.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>
                  <hi>John Drewet</hi>'s Teſtimony concerning <hi>Amariah Drewet</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis is the Teſtimony I have to bare for ray dear Unkle <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mariah Drewet,</hi> that he was a Man of an Innocent Life and Converſation; he was well ſeaſoned with the Grace of God, and was Faithful to the Truth, which I believe was more precious to him than all things beſides it: I was often with him in the time of his Sicknoſs, and he was preſerved in a ſweet fraine of Spirit, often ſpeaking of the Goodneſs of the Lord to him on his Death-Bed, and his Heart was filled with Praiſes to the Lord, in the openings of Life, to the great Comfort and Refreſh ment of thoſe Friends that were about him; he was a Man that was Faithful to the Lord in his Teſtimony, in the time of Tryal, and was bold for the Truth, and was Strength to thoſe that were Weak, and did encourage them to ſtand Faithful to the end; as bleſſed be the Lord he was preſerved, by the mighty Power of God, through all his Sufferings, which was great, both by Impriſonments and Spoiling of Goods, which he bore with much Cheerfulneſs, and ſtood ſtedfaſt without Wavering, bleſſed be the worthy Name of the Lord that did uphold him: I watched with him one Night, and I was ſweetly Refreſhed with him; he was much attended with the good Preſence of the Lord, and many ſweet Expreſſions came from him; ſome of which I wrote down from his own Mouth, what I could underſtand, but ſometimes he ſpoke ſo low that I could not well underſtand what he ſaid, but take this as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord, Strengthen my poor Body, that I may Praiſe thy Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dear Father, my Reſt is in thee, who pours out of thy Spirit into thy prophets, Isleſſed be the Lord forever and for evermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:108668:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>O the largneſs of thy Goodneſs that I feel. O Lord, bear my Cries, and bare up my Head in all my Exerciſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O thy ſweet Preſence and freſh Springs of Life that I feel, Glory and Henour, and Praiſes be unto thy Name forever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed Lord, a Weak Man, bus in thy Power do I receive Strength, thy Preſence and Love I feel, Bleſſed and Praiſed be thy Holy Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord help me and keep me cloſe to thy Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord attend my dear Wife with thy Preſence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some more Words that he ſpoke at another time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O thou mighty</hi> Jehovah, <hi>before whom all Nations are but as a drop of a Bucket, and as the ſmall duſt of the Ballance; thou who weigheſt the Mountains in Scales, and the Hills as in a Ballance; Mighty art thou in Power, but the World will not believe in thee, nor in thy Son Chriſt Jeſus, that they may be Saved;</hi> and much more to his purpoſe that was not taken.</p>
               <p>O my dear Unlſe, the great loſs I have of thee hath coſt me many a Tear, but our Loſs is thy Gain, who was Faithful unto the Death, and haſt obtained a Crown of Life, and an entrance into that Inheritance that ſhall never ſade away, where thy Roſt is fore with the Lord forever, in which I am well ſatisfied.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>John Drewet.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>Theophila Townſond's <hi>Teſtimony conterning the Life, Death and Sufferings of</hi> Amariah Drewet <hi>lately Deceaſed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE was an Innocent Upright Man, one that bore a good and faithful Teſtimony for the Lord in his Day and Time, both in Doing and Suffering, and finiſhed his Teſtimony with Joy, as through the Goodneſs and Mercy of the Lord I was made a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Witneſs; having a Living Sence upon my Spirit of the Living Preſence of the Lord, that did accompany him in the time of his Sickneſs, it often tendered his Heart, and refreſhed his Soul, that in the ſence of Gods Love, and in the riſing of Divine Life his Mouth was often opened to thoſe that came to viſit him, and alſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108668:5"/>to them that were about him of his own Family and Relations, in good. Advice and tender Counſel to them to be Faithful to the Lord, and to abide in his pure Fear, that they might have Peace when they come to a Dying Bed; as ſaid he, <hi>Through the Goodneſs of the Lord I can ſay, I have true Peace with God, and if I Dye I am well ſatisfied it will be well with me, and it will be a happy Change for me; Bleſſed and Praiſed be the worthy Name of the Lord, whoſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to me hath been beyond Expreſſion; now in the time of my Weakneſs;</hi> and then he broke forth into ſinging high Praiſes to the Name of the Lord, and ſweetly ſounding forth Holy Renown and Living Thanks to the Living God, for his Goodneſs, and Mercies, and Bleſſings, to the great Comfort of thoſe that were in the hearing of it; this and much more to the ſame effect was ſpoken by him in the time of his Sickneſs, ſomething more of it may be menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in order, as way opens for it; and firſt ſhall ſpake a little more of his Life and Sufferings; he was Open-hearted, Kind, Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Tender, his Heart and Houſe was open to receive the Lords Meſſengers and Miniſters that travilled in his Work and Service, and he deſired much to have them with him, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained them with Cheerfulneſs: He was a Man attended with great Sufferings in this laſt Perfecution, which was very Hot and Violent, here in this Town of <hi>Cirencester,</hi> in the County of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> the place of his abode; but he ſtood in his Teſtimony ſtedfaſt, and was bold for the holy Truth, notwithſtanding all the Rage and Fury of our Perſecutors, which was great againſt us for ſeveral Years, of which he had his ſhare both by Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and loſs of Goods; he had his Doors Broke, and his Goods Seized ſeveral times, till they had Seized all that was in the Houſe, and the Officers returned anſwer unto the Juſtice, that there was nothing to be had; but he bore all with Patience, and kept con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to Meetings, and when the Meeting-Houſe-Doors were Nailed up, and Friends kept out and met in the Yard he was not ſlack in coming to Aſſemble with them, and ſometime; kept Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in his Houſe, though the Juſtices frequently in their own Perſons did viſit our Meetings ſeveral Years together: But bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord whoſe Power and Preſence was with us and whoſe powerful Arm did uphold us, and keep us out of the Fear of Man, which was my Cry to the Lord, that in his pure Fear we
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108668:5"/>might be preſerved unto the end, and Gods Power was over all Bleſſed and Praiſed be his worthy Name forever and for ever more; who is not wanting to his Faithful People, but is their exceeding great Reward; who hath Rewarded this our dear Friend, and deceaſed Brother, with a Bleſſing of Reſt and Peace, in that Kingdom that never has End, and hath received him into the Boſom of his Love, where he ſhall ſolice his Soul forever and forever.</p>
               <p>This Innocent Man, who had been a great Sufferer by them ſeveral ways, too much here to mention; he bore it all with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience, and conſtantly frequented the Meetings of the Lords Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called <hi>Quakers,</hi> where he was a Strength to the Weak, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging them to Faithfulneſs.</p>
               <p>We may ſee a difference between the Death of the Righteous and the Death of the Wicked, for this Innocent Man <hi>A. D.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, upon his Dying-Bed often ſignified, <hi>That he was ſatisfied, that if he Dyed, it would be well with him, and it would be a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Change for him;</hi> Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord over all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, who is never wanting to his faithful People.</p>
               <p>The Sufferings which <hi>A. D.</hi> under went did not ſtarttle him, but with Boldneſs and holy Confidence he bore his Teſtimony for the Truth, and againſt his Perſecutors unchriſtian Proceedings which was contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye would that Men ſhould do unto you, do you the ſame to them:</hi> And he often adviſed them to ceaſe from Preſecution, and ſo eaſed his Spirit in clearing himſelf of them, and left it at their Doors, and left the Iſſue to the Lord, who hath taken him out of the reach of all his Enemies, and received him into that Reſt which is Glorious, where he ſhall ſolice his Soul in the Boſom of Divine Sweetneſs, Endleſs Bleſſedneſs, and Tryumph in Heavenly Glory forever and forever, of which he had a living ſence and feeling in his Life time, Magnified forever be the worthy Name of the Lord, for his Goodneſs to his People, for he is an exceeding great Reward to them that Fear before him, and put their Truſt in him; <hi>for the Righteous ſhall ſhine as the Stars forever and ever, and their Memorial is Bleſſed; but the Name of the Wicked ſhall Rot, and they ſhall Periſh forever, like their own Dung,</hi> as the Scriptures ſay; and though many Men perceive not the difference between the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108668:6"/>Death of the Righteous and of the Wicked, becauſe both go down to the Grave in like manner: It hath pleaſed God of his Mercy and Goodneſs to let us ſee a difference, as is apparent by this our dear Brother <hi>A. D.</hi> whoſe Dying-Bed was made comfortable to him, through the Comfort of Gods Love, in and through Chriſt Jeſus to his Soul, as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>The Righteous ſhall Sing for Joy of Heart, when the Wicked ſhall Howl for Vexation of Spirit;</hi> ſo in this Life the difference between the Death of the Righteous and the Wicked, the Joy and Comfort of the one, and the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and Miſery of the other; for the Righteous know and are aſſured, that before they put off this Houſe of Clay, that they have a Habitation not made with Hands, eternal in the Heavens, and their Peace is ſure with the Lord God, through the Son of of his Love, and that for evermore, as this faithful Servant of the Lord, before mentioned, often gave Teſtimony of in the time of his Sickneſs, of the aſſurance of his Peace with God, whoſe living Preſence did accompany him to his End; as long as he could ſpeak he made mention of it, ſaying, <hi>Often the Lords ſweet Preſence is with me beyond my expectation.</hi> When I came firſt to ſee him, he ſaid, <hi>He was freely given up in the will of God, whether to Live or Dye,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>if the Lord ſee it good to take me, it will be well with me, and it will be a happy Change for me;</hi> and he was ſo filled with the Joy of Gods Salvation, that he ſung for Joy of Heart, and Praiſed the Lord as with an heavenly Harp, as one of them that ſtood before the Throne of God and the Lamb, having the Harps of God in their Hands, and they Sung a new Song be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne, that none could learn but thoſe that were Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the Earth: My Soul was Refreſhed to ſee and feel the heavenly frame of Spirit that he was in all along upon his Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Bed: Another time, when I came to viſit him, he took me by the Hand and ſaid, <hi>Thou haſt been a Faithful Friend, and a Help to me in the Truth all along, and I have had a tender eſteem for thee, and all honeſt-hearted faithful Friends, and that which I chiefly and moſt deſired, ever ſince I knew the bleſſed Truth of God, was, that the Lord would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve me faithful to himſelf and his holy Truth unto the End, and I bleſs his Name, he hath been very good to me all along, that nothing did diſcourage me in the time of Sufferings to weaken me, but rather as Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings increaſed; I was ſtronger, and was freely given up according to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108668:6"/>my weak Capacity, to anſwer the Lord, and do that which I underſtood was right in his ſight; I could never ſpeak much, but deſired to live to what I knew, and the Lord hath accepted of it, Praiſes to his Name; and I can truly ſay, that the only thing I aimed at, in deſiring this my dear Wife, was that ſhe might be helpful to me in the Truth, and the Lord did make her a help to me, I Bleſs and Praiſe his holy Name, for his goodneſs to me on every account:</hi> I ſaid to him, I am perſwaded if the Lord ſee it beſt to ſpare thee, and that it would make moſt for Gods Glory, and thy Good, the Lord will raiſe thee up again, he ſaid, <hi>I believe the ſame:</hi> And when his Relations put him upon it to ſend to ſome Phyſitian, he anſwered <hi>no, for I have that which is known to be good, and approved Medicines, and if theſe will not do me good, I do not expect help from Man; for if the Lord ſee good to take me to himſelf, all the Men upon the Earth cannot keep me alive, ſo I am given up in the will of the Lord:</hi> He was gently viſited with a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, not Violent, nor complaining much of Pain nor Dryth, but Weakneſs; ſo he ſaid to me when I came to viſit him, I asked him how he did, he ſaid, <hi>Weak in Body, but Strong in the Lord, Weak in the outward Man, but Strong in the inward, Bleſſed and Praiſed be the Holy Name of the Lord forever:</hi> And when he Slumbred, as ſoon as he awaked, his Mouth was opened with a Song of high Praiſes to the Lord, and when the People came in to viſit him, he had a Word in ſeaſon for them, warning young People to <hi>fear God, and watch againſt thoſe things that did Corrupt Youth, exhorting them to Faithfulneſs, that it might be well with them upon a Dying-Bed, as it is with me,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Praiſes to the Lord forever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I was with him when he Departed, and I can truly ſay, the Lord gave me a ſence of his Condition, and I travelled with him under the Pangs of Death, in a fellow-feeling of the Exerciſe he was in, and when Death touched his Heart, I bore a part with him, in a ſympathiſing Spirit, and travelled in Spirit with him before the Lord for his Deliverance; and when Death was upon his Body, I felt the Reſurrection of the Life of Jeſus with his Soul, ready to receive him into that Heavenly Manſion of Glory, and Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Reſt and Peace with the Lord, which the Lord hath prepared for his People, which he had the earneſt of in his Life time, even the earneſt of the Spirit, that ſealed to him the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of that Inheritance that ſhall never fade away, into which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108668:7"/>he is entered and gathered, into that fulneſs that is Incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, which God the Father, in and through Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, had prepared for him, where Heavenly Joy and Gladneſs, and Divine Comfort, and Laſting Peace is and will be his Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for evermore.</p>
               <p>He departed this Life the 25th day of the 7th Morth 1687. about the 6th Hour in the Evening, he lay for about half an hour as if he had been in a ſweet Sleep, and went away quietly, like a Lamb, without Sigh or Groan; his dear Wife and Family have a great Loſs in parting with him, and I may ſay, we all miſs him, and I can ſay, my Heart hath been often tendered and broken into Tears of Sorrow for the loſs of him, but mixt with Joy in a ſenſe of his happy State; but in ſubmiſſion to the Will of God, I am well ſatisfied the Lord beſt knows when it is the fitteſt ſeaſon to take his own unto himſelf; and for this our dear Friend, he is now in a Habitation of Safety, out of all danger of falling into Temptation, or of being hurt by any of the Wiles of the Enemy, and the deſire of my Soul is, that all that know the Truth may walk in the ſame way, and travel in the Juſt Mans Path, as he did, that they may arrive at the ſame Haven of Reſt and Peace with him, and all the Sanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, in the Kingdom of God, World without End, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was Buried the 27th Day of the 7th Month, and was acompanied to the Grave, with many good Friends, and the Power and Preſence of the Lord was with us, and that Life that was with him, to his joy, upon his Dying-Bed, Spake forth the Praiſe &amp; Goodneſs of the Lord at his Burial, though his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Servants of the Lord, that did acompany him to his Grave: this was upon me to Publiſh for the Good and Beneſit of thoſe that are left behind; even of all tender People to whom this may come, that they may ſo Live, and ſo Walk, that they may be made Pertakers of the fame joy, which is obtained through Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, and obedient to the Light of his free Spirit who is the leader of his People; and this lead him, our dear Friend before mentioned, out of Sin into the way of Peace, this is the Holy Ghoſt, the Comforter; that which Chriſt Jeſus promiſed his Diſciples to ſend, to Lead them into all Truth; and farther ſaid, as the Scripture teſtifies, <hi>That he ſhall Convince the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108668:7"/>World of Sin, of Righteouſneſs, and of Judgment,</hi> and it is the ſame that Convinces of Sin, that leads out of Sin, and gives Victory over Sin to all that believe in it, and are willing to deny them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and take up their daily Croſs, and follow him; they come to know the aſſurance of Peace &amp; Reſt with the Lord before they go out of the Body, ſo the thoughts of Death is not terrible to ſuch, as it is to the Wicked, for Death is the King of Terrors to the Wicked, becauſe the way of Truth they have not known. <hi>For there is no Peace to the Wicked,</hi> ſaith the God of the Righteous, and they are made Witneſſes of it through faith in Chriſt Jeſus: who are ſubject, to his Light and Grace in their own Heart and Conſciences; but wo to the Wicked, it will go ill with them; they ſhall Eat the Fruits of their own doings, and go down to their Graves in Sorow, if they do not Repent of their Wickedneſs, and turn from the Evil of their Doings, and obey the Light of the Son of God, that they may be led out of Darkneſs, into his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous Light, and by it be turned from the Power of Satan to the great power of God, that they may know the good word of Life that is quick and Powerful, as Sharp and Sharper then any two Edged Sword, that divides aſunder even Soul and Spirit, and between Bones and Marrow, that Ingrafted Word of God (that is able to ſave the Soul) Chriſt Jeſus the Word of God, the Light of the World, as he ſaid of himſelf: and again he ſaid, <hi>He that believes in me ſhall not abide in Darkneſs:</hi> and the Scripture further teſtifies; <hi>that in him was Life, and the Life was the Light of men;</hi> ſo the Life of Jeſus is the Light of men; ſo I would adviſe all to take heed how they Slight the Light, both Profeſſors and Prophain, or how you Villifie the Light, and ſay, <hi>It is Inſufficient to Lead to Life and Peace;</hi> for in ſo doing you Slight and Villifie the Life of Jeſus, and the Grace of God that brings Salvation, which the Scriptures ſaith <hi>Hath appeared to all men, and teacheth to deny ungodlineſs and World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Luſt, and to Live Godly, and Righteouſly, and Soberly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Evil World;</hi> therefore in the Love of God I intreat you both Profeſſors and Prophain Love the Light, and the Grace and Truth that comes by Jeſus Chriſt, who is God, Salvation to the ends of the Earth, and there is no other Name Given
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108668:8"/>under Heaven by which any can be Saved, but by the Name of Jeſus, the true Light that Lighteth Every man that comes into the World, as the Scriptures ſaith, <hi>That God is Light, and in him is no Darkneſs at all,</hi> and this was the Meſſage the holy Apoſtle had to deliver, and this was the Work that he had to do, <hi>To turn People from Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan to the Power of God;</hi> ſo here People may ſee the Scriptures do declare, that God is Light, and Chriſt is Light, and they that ſlight this Heavenly Divine Light, ſlight both God and Chriſt Jeſus, and ſo are liable to Periſh in their Gain-ſaying and Rebellion againſt the Light, and never be made Pertakers of Gods Salvation; therefore I intreat all People, that have any tenderneſs towards the Lord, or any true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the welfare of their own Souls, both Profeſſors and Prophain, Neighbours, Kindred and Acquaintance, Love the Light that convinces of Sin, and reproves in ſecret for every evil Deed, and believe in it, that you may be ſaved from the Power of the Deſtroyer by it; the ſame that Convinces of Sin Leads out of Sin, and gives Victory over Sin, and brings into Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Peace with God the Father, in and through his Son Chriſt Jeſus; and I teſtifie in the holy Fear of the Lord, and in the tender Love of God, that opens in my Heart and Soul unto the Children of Men, that there is no other way to Salvation; for in Chriſt, the Light, is the univerſal Love of God held forth to all People; for he delights not in the death of a Sinner, but would have all to come to the knowledg of the Truth and be ſaved, who is calling his People out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> out of Confuſion, <hi>Come out of her my People, and touch no unclean thing, and I will Receive you, be not pertakers of her Sins, leſt you are pertakers of her Plagues.</hi> So I intreat you, for the Lords ſake, and for the good of your own Souls, draw near to the Lord, and he will draw near unto you, ſeek him while he is to be found; and call upon him while he is near, for he is not far off from Every one of you, that your Peace may be ſure with the Lord for evermore; which is the true deſire of my Soul for you all, who am your Friend (and one that Travels for the Proſperity of <hi>Sion</hi>) known by the Name of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Theophila Townſend</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:108668:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Charles Marſhall</hi>'s Teſtimony concerning <hi>Amariah Drewet.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe foregoing Teſtimonies are concerning the Life and Death of our dear Friend <hi>Amariah Drewet.</hi> I alſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had certain knowledg of him, and converſation with him, have this Teſtimony to give concerning him, <hi>Viz.</hi> That he was a man fearing God and eſchewing Evil, of a tender Spirit having the Awe of God in his Heart; he greatly loved the Goſpel of Peace, and thoſe that were ſent of God to Preach it in the Power and Demonſtration of his Eternal Spirit; his Heart was made glad when the Power of the Lord reached and affected the Heart of his Neighbours; becauſe he greatly deſired their Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Welfare; more might be ſaid of his Life, Sufferings and Death, but I refer to the foregoing Teſtimonies of Ear and Eye Witneſſes of his latter End, by whoſe Teſtimonies it appears, that as he Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſo he Dyed, in the living enjoyments of Gods Immortal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, &amp; felt Refreſhment from the Throne of his Eternal Glory.</p>
               <p>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> now, Oh Inhabitants of <hi>Cirenceſter,</hi> unto whom the Word of Eternal Life hath been Preached, in a clear Demonſtration of the Spirit and Power of the moſt High, and over whom hath been a bleſſed day of Viſitation, tenderly conſider your States and Conditions, and Imbrace that great Bleſſing, namely, <hi>A being turned every one from the Evil of his doings; &amp; ſeek the Lord while he may be found, call upon him while he is near at band ſtriving with you by the Spirit of his Son Chriſt Jeſus, and knocking at the Door of your Hearts: Oh, let the Saviour In, that ye may be ſaved from Sin, and Redeemed from the Nature of it.</hi> So is the Bleſſed end of Chriſt Jeſus his coming anſwered, namely, <hi>To deſtroy the Works of the Devil:</hi> Conſider in the Dread of the moſt High, your time is ſhort, and not only ſhort, but alſo uncertain, therefore remember your latter End, that as you muſt follow your Righteous Neighbour through Death, ſo it may be that your latter End may be like his, that living the Life of the Righteous ye may enjoy Eternal Life, when time in this World with you will be no more; that through the following the Spiritual Pillar of Fire, which leads out of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108668:9"/>
                  <hi>Egypt,</hi> you may obtain the Spiritual <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Reſt and Sabboth of God.</p>
               <p>And unto thoſe that do profeſs the ſame Truth, that our dear Friend deceaſed did, in theſe parts; Ah, prize your precious Time, and the ſeaſon of Love and Kindneſs, that is over you, and the Mercy attending you; and walk worthy of it, and give not way to a Spiritual Idleneſs, which leads into a Spiritual Slumber, through which the Lamp goes out, and unreadineſs to anſwer the Midnight Cry, and that which follows is Dreadfull, a Shutting of the Door; therefore, while its called to Day, anſwer the Lords Call and tender Viſitation, that both Calling and Election may be made ſure; ſo will the Lord delight in you, and bleſs you, and water you, that in the Innocent Life of Chriſt Jeſus ye might Live, that your part in the firſt reſurrection ye may obtain, and thereby be preſerved from the power of the ſecond Death; ſo that on the Dying Bed you may hear that Joyfull Teſtimony, <hi>Bleſſed are the Dead that die in the Lord, ye ſaith the Spirit they reſt from their Labonrs, and their Works ſhall follow them.</hi> And now, dear Friends, as ye deſire this Portion, and to Honour and Renown the great Name of our Merciful and Tender Father, be ſtirred up to great Diligence, redeeming Time, loving and obeying the ſweet redeeming Power of the Lord, that his Bleſſed Work, bleſſedly begun in the Hearts of many, may be accompliſhed, that you being made free from the Law of Sin and Death, by the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, may lay down your Heads in Peace, and enjoy the Crown of Immortallity, which is the Lot and Portion of all that follow the <hi>Lamb</hi> in the Work of Regeneration: And ſo, dear Friends, in the Love of God, theſe few Lines, upon this occaſion, were on my Heart, to bring in a Teſtimony to the Lords goodneſs, that gave our dear Friend, that had followed the Lord faithfully, ſo ſweet a Paſſage out of this Life to injoy Immortal Life for evermore.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Charles Marſhall.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>London</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>the </hi>25th <hi>of the</hi> 11th <hi>Month</hi> 1687</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:108668:9"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
